<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Achievement Gap on Data Science in Education</title>
    <link>/categories/achievement-gap/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Achievement Gap on Data Science in Education</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Daniel Anderson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/achievement-gap/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Geographic Variance in Achievement Gaps</title>
      <link>/post/modeling-geographic-variance-in-achievement-gaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/modeling-geographic-variance-in-achievement-gaps/</guid>
      <description>This is the fourth and (probably) final post in a series of posts about estimating, visualizing, exploring, and now modeling achievement gap variation between schools using publicly available data.
Let’s start by loading the data directly from my website. The code below should provide you with achievement gap data
library(tidyverse) d &amp;lt;- read_csv(&amp;quot;https://github.com/datalorax/site/raw/master/content/post/v-geocoded.csv&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% mutate_at(vars(v, Longitude, Latitude), as.numeric) Introduction and background What we’d really like to do is understand how much geography accounts for achievement gap variability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Geographic Variation in Achievement Gaps</title>
      <link>/post/exploring-geographic-variation-in-achievement-gaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/exploring-geographic-variation-in-achievement-gaps/</guid>
      <description>This is, basically, the third post in a series of posts about estimating and, now, exploring achievement gap variation between schools. The first post described the method, while the second applied the method to estimate achievement gaps for all schools reporting data on students coded as Hispanic and White in California. That post included some preliminary explorations of the data, but this post will take that further by looking at the variance geographically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating important things with public data</title>
      <link>/post/estimating-important-things-with-public-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/estimating-important-things-with-public-data/</guid>
      <description>Intro One of the neatest things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned about in the last few years is how to estimate effect sizes from coarsened data. The original article discussed using the method with publicly available data reported by statewide education agencies, and that&amp;rsquo;s the approach I&amp;rsquo;ll use here too. But more generally, the method could be applied in any situation in which a continuous distribution is reported out in ordinal bins.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>