<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science in Education</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Data Science in Education</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>daniela@uoregon.edu (Daniel Anderson)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>daniela@uoregon.edu (Daniel Anderson)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>esvis: Part 1</title>
      <link>/post/esvis-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>daniela@uoregon.edu (Daniel Anderson)</author>
      <guid>/post/esvis-part-1/</guid>
      <description>This is the first of a series of posts to introduce my new esvis R package, why I think it’s important, and some of its capabilities. As of this writing the current version on CRAN is 0.0.1, so it’s obviously still fresh and may have some bugs. If you find any, please let me know. You can install the package like you would any other on R
install.packages(&amp;quot;esvis&amp;quot;) or if you’d prefer the sometimes bugging but more feature-heavy development version, install from github with devtools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>daniela@uoregon.edu (Daniel Anderson)</author>
      <guid>/page/about/</guid>
      <description>I work as a research associate for Behavioral Research and Teaching, a grant-based center in the College of Education at the University of Oregon. My career in research began in measurement and psychometrics and I still do consulting work in that area. However, my research focus has mostly moved towards data science and the economics of education. In other words, I am interested in the intersection of computer programming and statistics, as applied to large-scale data, to understand macro-level features of the educational system (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Presentations</title>
      <link>/page/conference_pres/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>daniela@uoregon.edu (Daniel Anderson)</author>
      <guid>/page/conference_pres/</guid>
      <description>National and International Conferences  Anderson, D., Stevens, J. J., and Nese, J. F. T. (April, 2017). Visualizing Achievement Gaps Across the Full Distribution. Paper presented at the annual meeting of the National Council on Measurement in Education, San Antonio, TX.
 Stevens, J. J., Anderson, D., Nese, J. F. T., and Tindal, G. (April, 2017). Using Effect Size Measures to Estimate and Report Achievement Gaps. Paper presented at the annual meeting of the National Council on Measurement in Education, San Antonio, TX.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/page/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>daniela@uoregon.edu (Daniel Anderson)</author>
      <guid>/page/publications/</guid>
      <description>Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles  Fien, H., Anderson, D., Nelson, N. J., Baker, S. K., Kennedy, P. (in press). Examining the Impact and School-Level Predictors of Impact Variability of an 8th Grade Reading Intervention on At-Risk Students’ Reading Achievement. Learning Disabilities Research &amp;amp; Practice.
 Anderson, D., Kahn, J, and Tindal, G. (2017). Exploring the Robustness of a Unidimensional Item Response Theory Model with Empirically Multidimensional Data. Applied Measurement in Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software</title>
      <link>/page/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>daniela@uoregon.edu (Daniel Anderson)</author>
      <guid>/page/software/</guid>
      <description>esvis Anderson, D. (2017). esvis: Visualization and Estimation of Effect Sizes. R package version 0.1.0. CRAN GitHub
The purpose of esvis is primarily to visualize differences in two or more distributions. It is an implementation and extension of ideas discussed by Andrew Ho (see, for example, here). Non-parametric methods for effects sizes are also implemented. For an introduction to the package, see here. The package is under active development.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>