<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science in Education</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Data Science in Education</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Daniel Anderson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating important things with public data</title>
      <link>/post/estimating-important-things-with-public-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/estimating-important-things-with-public-data/</guid>
      <description>Intro One of the neatest things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned about in the last few years is how to estimate effect sizes from coarsened data. The original article discussed using the method with publicly available data reported by statewide education agencies, and that&amp;rsquo;s the approach I&amp;rsquo;ll use here too. But more generally, the method could be applied in any situation in which a continuous distribution is reported out in ordinal bins.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking into #KeepFamiliesTogether</title>
      <link>/post/looking-into-keepfamiliestogether/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/looking-into-keepfamiliestogether/</guid>
      <description>This week I&amp;rsquo;m at the Seattle branch of the Summer Institute on Computational Social Science. Today, we discussed digital trace data and spent some time thinking about different sources of digital trace data. One of the easiest sources is twitter, and thanks to Mike Kearney, it&amp;rsquo;s easily accessible in R via the {rtweet} package!
I joined a group addressing a topic I find myself dwelling on throughout the day - the immigration crisis at the border.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peeking behind the curtain with {slidex}</title>
      <link>/post/peeking-behind-the-curtain-with-slidex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/peeking-behind-the-curtain-with-slidex/</guid>
      <description>I gave a lightning talk (slides here) this past weekend at the second annual Cascadia R Conference that was focused on creating and contributing new themes to the {xaringan} package, which is essentially a really well thought out and well-organized R Markdown wrapper around the remark.js package for producing beautiful HTML slides. At the end of that talk, I announced the work-in-progress version of my new R package, {slidex}, for converting Microsoft PowerPoint slides to R Markdown, and specifically {xaringan}, with a single function.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing an R Package Basics (and why I think you should)</title>
      <link>/post/why-i-think-you-should-write-an-r-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/why-i-think-you-should-write-an-r-package/</guid>
      <description>On April 10, 2018, I gave a talk entitled Developing your first R package: A case study with esvis for the Eugene R Users Group. Although I discussed my esvis package, the focus of the talk was really on tools and tips for developing R pacakges. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll go over some of the content in that talk, and discuss why I think you should develop an R package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Website Theme!</title>
      <link>/post/new-website-theme/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/new-website-theme/</guid>
      <description>This post has needed to be writtend for a little while, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been busy with the actual work of redesigning my website (in fact, I have a number of posts that are backlogged). This post will have a little bit of code (all of it CSS, rather than R), but mostly it&amp;rsquo;s just about my journey and things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned.
Getting started with Blogdown In Yihui&amp;rsquo;s introduction to blogdown he advocates for simpler themes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference Presentations</title>
      <link>/vita/conference_pres/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/conference_pres/</guid>
      <description>National and International Conferences  Anderson, D., and Tindal, G. (October, 2018). Changes in status and performance for students with learning disabilities. Poster presented at the annual meeting of the Council for Learning Disabilities, Portland, OR.
 Anderson, D., and Stevens, J. J. (April, 2018). Exploring and visualizing achievement and school effects. Paper presented at the annual meeting of the National Council on Measurement in Education, New York, NY.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>License</title>
      <link>/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/license/</guid>
      <description>MIT License
Copyright &amp;copy; 2018 Daniel Anderson
Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the &amp;ldquo;Software&amp;rdquo;), to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharing some functions from my personal R package</title>
      <link>/post/sharing-some-functions-from-my-personal-r-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sharing-some-functions-from-my-personal-r-package/</guid>
      <description>In this post I basically just wanted to share some recent developments that I&amp;rsquo;ve made to my personal R package {sundry}. All of the recent advancements have been made to work with the tidyverse, so things like group_by should work seamlessly. If you feel like giving the package a whirl, I&amp;rsquo;d love any feedback you have or bugs you may find. At this point the package is only on github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A tidyeval use case</title>
      <link>/post/a-tidyeval-use-case/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-tidyeval-use-case/</guid>
      <description>A relatively routine process for me is to combine multiple files into a single data frame by row. For example, the data might be stored in separate CSV files by grade and content area, but I want to load them all and treat it as a single data frame with a grade and content indicator. A good default for this sort of process, is to keep all the variables that are present in any data file, and pad with missingness for the files that don&amp;rsquo;t have that specific variable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>esvis: Binned Effect Size Plots</title>
      <link>/post/esvis-binned-effect-size-plots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/esvis-binned-effect-size-plots/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share one of the more unique plots from esvis - the binned effect size plot. The overall purpose of the binned effect size plot is to evaluate if the differences between two distributions are consistent across the scale. We&amp;rsquo;ll start with a quick example from the package, and then move to a simulated data example.
Quick example The API for esvis is consistent across functions, so we use the same outcome ~ predictor forumula as the first argument, followed by the data for all functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alluvial Diagrams with ggforce</title>
      <link>/post/alluvial-plots-with-ggforce/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/alluvial-plots-with-ggforce/</guid>
      <description>Today I wanted to quickly share my first real attempt at making an alluvial diagram. For those not familiar (and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t previously) an alluvial diagram is a type of flow plot that is essentially equivalent to a sankey diagram. The difference is that while sankey diagrams show flow for different categorical variables, alluvial plots show change over time. To produce the alluvial diagram below, I&amp;rsquo;ll be using the development version of the excellent ggforce package written by Thomas Lin Pedersen, who&amp;rsquo;s not only incredibly talented, but also a good follow on twitter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Statewide School Ratings with US Census Tracts</title>
      <link>/post/mapping-statewide-school-ratings-with-us-census-tracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/mapping-statewide-school-ratings-with-us-census-tracts/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share some work related to geo-spatial mapping, statewide school ratings, and US Census Bureau data using census tracts. Specifically, I wanted to investigate whether there was a relation between the median housing price in an area, and the statewide achievement ratings for schools in the corresponding area. There is a strong relation between socio-economic status and student achievement, but less is known about how statewide ratings for schools relate to the demographics of the corresponding area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>esvis: Part 1</title>
      <link>/post/esvis-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/esvis-part-1/</guid>
      <description>This is the first of a series of posts to introduce my new esvis R package, why I think it&amp;rsquo;s important, and some of its capabilities. As of this writing the current version on CRAN is 0.0.1, so it&amp;rsquo;s obviously still fresh and may have some bugs. If you find any, please let me know. You can install the package like you would any other on R
install.packages(&amp;quot;esvis&amp;quot;)  or if you&amp;rsquo;d prefer the sometimes buggy but more feature-heavy development version, install from github with devtools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/aera19-rr-p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/aera19-rr-p1/</guid>
      <description>Transparent and Reproducible Research with R (Part 1)    class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Transparent and Reproducible Research with R (Part 1) ## And a bit of git/GitHub ### Daniel Anderson ### Joshua M Rosenberg ### April 7, 2019 --- class: inverse background-image:url(https://media.giphy.com/media/yoJC2A59OCZHs1LXvW/giphy.gif) background-size:contain --- # Agenda ### First two hours - Introduction (8:00 - 8:45) - Who we are, who participants are and why they&#39;re here (15 min.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/aera19-rr-p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/aera19-rr-p2/</guid>
      <description>Transparent and Reproducible Research with R (Part 2)   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Transparent and Reproducible Research with R (Part 2) ## And a bit of git/GitHub ### Daniel Anderson ### Joshua M Rosenberg ### April 7, 2019 --- # Agenda # Last two hours - Advanced R Markdown functionality (10:15 - 11:00 minutes) - Formatting tables (20 min.) &amp;lt;!-- DA --&amp;gt; - Creating manuscripts to submit for publication (via {papaja}; 25 min.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/cascadia18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/cascadia18/</guid>
      <description>Contribute to Open Source with Pretty Slides   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Contribute to Open Source with Pretty Slides ## (And a short preview of a WIP package) ### Daniel Anderson ### June 2, 2018 --- class: center, middle # xaringan ### /ʃæ.&#39;riŋ.ɡæn/ --- # What it is .pull-left[ * HTML-based slides * Produced with R Markdown * Styled with CSS ] .pull-right[ ![](assets/img/rmd.png) ] .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/datasci-09-11-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/datasci-09-11-18/</guid>
      <description>My research and the COE   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # My research and the COE ### Daniel Anderson ### September 11, 2018 --- ![](ncaase-logo.png) ### Large inter-state collaborative * Oregon, Arizona, Pennsylvania, North Carolina * Lots of data and data sharing agreements + State testing data for every student in each state, Grades 3-8, in Reading and Math (some science) + Number of years varies by state, but generally there&#39;s about a decade * Focus on growth-modeling, accountability policies, and between-school --- class: bottom left background-image:url(growth-projections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/eugene_rug/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/eugene_rug/</guid>
      <description>Developing Your First R Package   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Developing Your First R Package ## A Case Study with esvis ### Daniel Anderson ### 04-10-2018 --- # Want to follow along? If you&#39;d like to follow along, pleae make sure you have the following packages installed ```r install.packages(c(&#34;tidyverse&#34;, &#34;esvis&#34;, &#34;devtools&#34;, &#34;roxygen2&#34;, &#34;usethis&#34;)) ``` --- # #whomi &amp;lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; href=&#34;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/font-awesome/4.7.0/css/font-awesome.min.css&#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DJAnderson07&#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-github fa-2x&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/ncme18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/ncme18/</guid>
      <description>Exploring and Visualizing School Achievement and School Effects   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Exploring and Visualizing School Achievement and School Effects ### Daniel Anderson  Joseph Stevens ### 04/16/18 --- # Introduction * Much recent focus on open data in research generally * Open data tend to be rare in educational research + Privacy concerns .footnote[Slides available at [dandersondata.com/talks/ncme18](http://www.dandersondata.com/talks/ncme18)] -- .Large[.bolder[.center[NCLB Required Publicly Available Data]]] -- * School-level data * Percent proficent in each of at least four proficiency categories * Disaggregated by student subgroups --- # Making Comparisons .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/ncme19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/ncme19/</guid>
      <description>Evaluating Content-Related Validity Evidence Using Text Modeling   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Evaluating Content-Related Validity Evidence Using Text Modeling ### Daniel Anderson ### Brock Rowley ### Sondra Stegenga ### P. Shawn Irvin ### Joshua M. Rosenberg --- # Background ### Content-related validity evidence -- * One five major sources of validity evidence (as outlined by the [*Standards*](https://www.apa.org/science/programs/testing/standards)) -- * Does the content represented in the test represent the targeted content?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/psych-seminar19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/psych-seminar19/</guid>
      <description>Some data viz advice   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Some data viz advice ### Daniel Anderson ### Wednesday, April 24 --- # #whoami .pull-left[ * Research Assistant Professor: Behavioral Research and Teaching, University * Dad (two daughters: 7 and 4 (almost 5)) * Primary areas of interest + 💗💗R💗💗 and computational research + Open data, open science, and reproducible workflows + Growth modeling, achievement gaps, and variance between educational institutions (particularly spatially) ] &amp;lt;img src=&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/sicss-seattle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/sicss-seattle/</guid>
      <description>Community Features and School Achievement Gaps   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Community Features and School Achievement Gaps ## And some other stuff ### Daniel Anderson ### June 22, 2018 --- # Introduction * Much recent focus on open data in research generally * Open data tend to be rare in educational research + Privacy concerns -- .Large[.bolder[.center[NCLB Required Publicly Available Data]]] -- * School-level data * Percent proficent in each of at least four proficiency categories * Disaggregated by student subgroups --- # Illustrating one approach * Simulate some data from two distributions + Group 1: `\(n = 200\)`, `\(\mu = 200\)`, `\(\sigma = 10\)` + Group 2: `\(n = 500\)`, `\(\mu = 210\)`, `\(\sigma = 8\)` * Cut Scores: 190, 205, 215 .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/uu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/uu/</guid>
      <description>Measurement, individual differences, and the promise of computational methods   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Measurement, individual differences, and the promise of computational methods ## Job talk for the University of Utah ### Daniel Anderson ### November 15, 2018 --- # My background ### Behavioral Research and Teaching * Research Assistant to Research Associate to Research Assistant Professor * Grant funded research shop at UO that mostly focuses on measurement + Curriculum Based Measurement (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/talks/vatech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/vatech/</guid>
      <description>Variance in Student Growth, Intervention Effects, and Achievement Gaps   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Variance in Student Growth, Intervention Effects, and Achievement Gaps ## Job talk for Virginia Tech ### Daniel Anderson ### March 25, 2019 --- # My background ### Behavioral Research and Teaching * Research Assistant to Research Associate to Research Assistant Professor * Grant funded research shop at UO that mostly focuses on measurement + Curriculum Based Measurement (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w1p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w1p1/</guid>
      <description>Oh the places you’ll go!   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Oh the places you’ll go! ## An introduction to the course and beyond ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 1, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Introductions * Syllabus * Introduce R ### Overall purpose of today: * Understand the course requirements * Get you excited about R! + This week will be a lot of me showing, and not a lot of you doing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w1p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w1p2/</guid>
      <description>Seeing the big picture   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Seeing the big picture ## The R ecosystem, and other tools in the data science pipeline ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 1, Class 2 --- background-image: url(http://r4ds.had.co.nz/diagrams/data-science.png) background-size:contain # The data science pipeline -- ### How do we go about this? --- class: inverse center middle background-image: url(../img/sky.jpg) background-size: cover # R Packages --- # &#34;Out of the box&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w2p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w2p1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to data visualization   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Introduction to data visualization ## Scatterplots with smooths, line plots ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 2, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Introduce ggplot2 * Discuss scatterplots and smooths * Discuss line plots * Lab --- # The *ggplot2* package Today, we&#39;ll primarily be covering the basics of the *ggplot2* package. &amp;lt;div align = &#34;left&#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;img src = .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w2p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w2p2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to data visualization   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Introduction to data visualization ## Distributions &amp;amp; categorical data ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 2, Class 2 --- # Agenda * Questions * New geoms! * Lab --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have? --- # geoms for today * `geom_histogram` * `geom_density` * `ggridges::geom_density_ridges` * `geom_boxplot` * `geom_violin` * `ggbeeswarm::*` * `geom_tile` * `geom_bar` * `geom_col` --- # Data for today * *fivethirtyeight* package + college_grad_students ```r install.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w3p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w3p1/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to data wrangling 1   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Introduction to data wrangling 1 ## dplyr and friends ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 3, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Questions * Basic data wrangling * Lab --- # First: Cool stuff share! * Equations within RMD look beautiful, but can be a pain + Must use \LaTeX (see examples [here](http://www.statpower.net/Content/310/R%20Stuff/SampleMarkdown.html)) -- ``` $$ \int_0^{2\pi} \sin x-dx $$ ``` -- .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w3p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w3p2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to data wrangling 2   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Introduction to data wrangling 2 ## dplyr and friends ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 3, Class 2 --- # Agenda * Questions * Workflows (quickly) * Importing data * A little more dplyr * Lab --- # Reading in data * We&#39;ll use the [{here}](https://github.com/r-lib/here) package + Allows you to not worry about paths so much + Helps reproducibility -- * In your R Studio project directory + Create a new folder called &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w4p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w4p1/</guid>
      <description>Dynamic Documents 1    class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Dynamic Documents 1 ## Intro to R Markdown ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 4, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Questions * R Markdown * Lab -- ### Learning objectives for today * Understand how to render R Markdown documents &amp;amp; mix code with text * Understand different chunk options * Understand inline code evaluation --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w4p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w4p2/</guid>
      <description>Intro to git and GitHub   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Intro to git and GitHub ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 4, Class 2 --- # Agenda * Questions * Intro to *git*/*GitHub* * Lab -- ### Learning objectives for today * Understand the basics of git and git vocabulary * Be able to create repos, push projects, commit changes * Begin collaborating on a project --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w5p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w5p1/</guid>
      <description>More git   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # More git ## And intro to dynamic APA manuscripts ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 5, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Questions * Revisit some *git*/*GitHub* * {papaja} * Lab -- ### Learning objectives for today * Understand how to render R Markdown documents into APA manuscripts * Understand how to include citations in an R Markdown document -- ### Objectives * Render an R Markdown document as an APA manuscript --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w5p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w5p2/</guid>
      <description>Dynamic Documents 2   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Dynamic Documents 2 ## APA Manuscripts ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 5, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Questions * Some leftover R Markdown + bold/italicize/code + TOC * Some {papaja} modifications * Equations * Lab -- ### Learning objectives for today * Understand how to include latex extensions in RMD * Be able to produce basic equations --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w6p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w6p2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to tidy data   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Introduction to tidy data ## (AKA what we should have covered before Alison’s visit) ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 6, Class 2 --- # Agenda * Introduce the concept of tidy data * Tidy a simple dataset together with `tidyr` * Summarize and transform tidy data with `dplyr` * Lab -- ### Learning objectives for today * Understand the concept of tidy data is useful * Understand and be able to apply the `gather` function --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w7p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w7p1/</guid>
      <description>Continuing our introduction to tidy data   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Continuing our introduction to tidy data ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 7, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Review tidy data * Cover a few more examples together * Lab + Work through Alison tidy data lab (based on Jenny Bryan&#39;s LOTR tidy data example) -- ### Learning objectives for today * Get more comfortable with tidy data * Get more fluent with `gather` --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w7p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w7p2/</guid>
      <description>Finishing up with tidy data   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Finishing up with tidy data ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 7, Class 2 --- # Agenda * Discuss `gather` and `spread` more -- ### Learning objectives for today * Get more comfortable with moving from wide to long * Understand when you may need to &#34;overgather&#34;, an how to best approach this --- # Reasons to prefer tidy data * More efficient storage and retrieval * More scalable * The *tidyverse* of tools will work much more efficiently --- # Read in the hiv data Note, you&#39;ll need to add `header = TRUE` to `import` to get it to treat the first row as column names instead of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w8p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w8p1/</guid>
      <description>Some data taming   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Some data taming ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 8, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Discuss variable types * &#34;Automatic&#34; factor re-leveling * Maybe some string manipulations (if time allows) * Lab -- ### Learning objectives for today * Get more comfortable with tidy data * Get more fluent with `gather` --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w9p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1-slides/w9p1/</guid>
      <description>Review   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Review ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 9, Class 1 --- # Agenda * Publishing slides with GitHub * Review where we&#39;ve been * Lab --- class: inverse center middle # Publishing slides w/GitHUb ### Demo (RMarkdown Slides and a quick note on {xaringan}) --- ## Tidyverse: Providing a grammar for... * Graphics (ggplot) * Data manipulations (dplyr) * Tidying data (tidyr) --- class: inverse center middle # dplyr --- ## dplyr: A grammar for data wrangling * `select()`: A subset of columns * `filter()`: A subset of rows * `mutate()`: Add or modify existing columns * `arrange()`: Rows in a ascending or descending order * `summarize()`: A variable according to other functions (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/educ611/slides/class1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/educ611/slides/class1/</guid>
      <description>Course Overview, Research Basics, &amp;amp; Intro to Validty   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Course Overview, Research Basics, &amp;amp; Intro to Validty ## EDUC 611: Class 1 ### Daniel Anderson ### Shawn Irvin ### August 31, 2018 --- class: inverse, bottom background-image: url(assets/img/welcome.jpg) background-size: cover --- # Who am I? .pull-left[ * Research Assistant Professor: Behavioral Research and Teaching * Dad (two daughters: 6 and 4) * Primary areas of interest + 💗💗R💗💗 and computational research + Open data, open science, and reproducible workflows + Growth modeling, achievement gaps, and variance between educational institutions ] .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/educ611/slides/class2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/educ611/slides/class2/</guid>
      <description>Validity, Sampling, and Measurement   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Validity, Sampling, and Measurement ## EDUC 611: Class 2 ### Daniel Anderson ### Shawn Irvin ### August 31, 2018 --- class:inverse right background-image:url(assets/img/clock.jpg) background-size:cover # Timing APA stuff until 4:45 Internal validity until 5:05 Internal validity activity until 5:30 External validity and randomness until 6:15 .lightblue[**Break until 6:40**] Types of samples until 7:00 Sampling activity until 7:15 Finishing up sampling until 7:30 Measurement until 8:20 ### If we have time at the end * Measurement activity --- # APA Stuff .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/educ611/slides/class3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/educ611/slides/class3/</guid>
      <description>Measurement &amp;amp; Experimental/Quasi-Experimental Designs   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Measurement &amp;amp; Experimental/Quasi-Experimental Designs ### Daniel Anderson ### Shawn Irvin ### August 7, 2018 --- class:inverse right background-image:url(assets/img/clock.jpg) background-size:cover # Timing Measurement until 5:15 Measurement Activity until 5:40 Causal inference until 6:05 .lightblue[**Break until 6:15**] Experimental Design until 6:30 RCTs until 7:00 Intro to quasi-experiments until 7:20 .yellow[Research Design Activity until 7:40] Midterm Discussion until 8:00 --- class:inverse right background-image:url(assets/img/measurement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w1/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to Multiple Regression!   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Welcome to Multiple Regression! ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 1 --- # Agenda * 👋 * What we&#39;re up to in this class * Brief intro to R * Review + Variance/covariance + Correlations - And why visualizations are important + Simple linear regression --- # Who am I? .pull-left[ * Research Assistant Professor: Behavioral Research and Teaching * Dad (two daughters: 6 and 4) * Primary areas of interest + 💗💗R💗💗 and computational research + Open data, open science, and reproducible workflows + Growth modeling, achievement gaps, and variance between educational institutions ] .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w10/</guid>
      <description>Regression for Prediction   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Regression for Prediction ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 10 --- # Agenda * Review lab from last class * Introduce regression modeling for prediction (rather than explanation) * Old-school methods * Criteria for assessing model accuracy * Bias-variance tradeoff &amp;amp; overfitting + `\(k\)`-fold cross-validation (quickly) --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w2/</guid>
      <description>MR w/two continuous IVs   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # MR w/two continuous IVs ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 2 --- # Agenda * A little bit of R * Reading in data * *ggplot2* basics * A little more review of simple linear regression * Calculation of intercept &amp;amp; slope * Extending the SLR model --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w3/</guid>
      <description>MR w/Categorical IVs   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # MR w/Categorical IVs ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 3 --- # Agenda * Reminder on dummy/effect coding + Factors in R * Example Scenarios * Lab --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have? --- # First things first Let&#39;s get some data! [demo] Please follow along. We&#39;ll load the `hsb2.sav` file. --- # Categorical Variables * So far we&#39;ve dealt with only continuous IVs + What if we have categorical variables?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w4/</guid>
      <description>Uncertainty and significance testing   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Uncertainty and significance testing ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 4 --- # Agenda * A little bit of R + Load some data + radiant demo * Uncertainty + Standard errors + Confidence intervals + p-values * Sample interpretations * Lab --- # Thinking about learning objectives I would really like you to leave this class being able to do the following: 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w5/</guid>
      <description>Model assumptions &amp;amp; Diagnostics   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Model assumptions &amp;amp; Diagnostics ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 5 --- # Agenda * Model Assumptions + LINE acronym for assumptions + Importance of exploring and visualizing your data first * Model Diagnostics * Outliers * Lab --- class: inverse center middle # Model Assumptions ![](http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/when_you_assume.png) .footnote[credit: xkcd] --- # .red[LINE] * **.red[L]**inearity * **.red[I]**ndependence of residual errors * Multivariate **.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w6/</guid>
      <description>Partial and Semi-Partial Correlations   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Partial and Semi-Partial Correlations ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 6 --- # Agenda * Review Lab * A few more notes on model assumptions * Partial and semi-partial correlations * Lab --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have? --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/wood.jpg) background-size:cover # Let&#39;s get some data --- # Residuals Last time, we talked about: -- * ordinary residuals: `\(Y&#39; - Y\)` -- * Standardized residuals: `\(e_{Si} = \frac{e_i}{s_{y.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w7/</guid>
      <description>Interactions   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Interactions ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 7 --- # Agenda * Review Exercise * Centering data * Standardized coefficients (briefly) * Interactions (this week and next) + Interactions between two categorical variables + Interactions between one categorical variable and one continuous variable + Interactions between two continuous variables * Lab --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w8/</guid>
      <description>Multi-model inference   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Multi-model inference ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 8 --- # Agenda * Review Exercise * Introducing multi-model comparisons + Revisiting squared semi-partial correlations from a multi-model approach + Testing differences between models * A brief foray into information criteria * More model comparisons + Comparing blocks of predictors + Thinking more about interactions * Lab --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr-slides/w9/</guid>
      <description>Dealing with collinearity and non-linearity   class: center, middle, inverse, title-slide # Dealing with collinearity and non-linearity ### Daniel Anderson ### Week 9 --- # Agenda * Review interactions exercise * Review the concept of (multi)collinearity * Introduce collinearity diagnostic tools + Tolerance + Variance Inflation Factor * Discuss nonlinearity + Polynomial approaches + Transformations (e.g., log) --- class: inverse middle center background-image:url(../img/chalkboard.jpg) background-size:cover # What questions do you have?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>I work as a research associate for Behavioral Research and Teaching, a grant-based center in the College of Education at the University of Oregon. My career in research began in measurement and psychometrics and I still do consulting work in that area. However, my research focus has mostly moved towards data science and the economics of education. In other words, I am interested in the intersection of computer programming and statistics, as applied to large-scale data, to understand macro-level features of the educational system (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advanced dplyr and More on RMarkdown</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w5p1/w5p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w5p1/w5p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Reviewing what we know Talk with your neighbor: How would you do each of the following using dplyr?  Extract only the first and third through ninth columns Extract the third column and any column that ends with &amp;ldquo;response&amp;rdquo; Reorder columns Extract only cases from students classified as English Language Learners (ELL) Create a new variable that represents the proportion of ELL students by grade Order the data in ascending or descending order Center a variable (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the course</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w10p1/w10p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w10p1/w10p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  A reminder: The R learning curve Agenda  Introduction to functions Introduction to Lists Introduction to the purrr package for working with lists Artificial example Walk through a real script (at least some of it)  Before we get started&amp;hellip;  There&amp;rsquo;s SO MUCH we still haven&amp;rsquo;t talked about
 Haven&amp;rsquo;t even discussed modeling! Version control (git/github) Functional programming (get a bit today) Object oriented programming  We also briefly discussed a few important topics</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data viz best practices</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w3p2/w3p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w3p2/w3p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Discuss some of the underlying theory and empirical research behind data visualizaitons  What makes a figure good? What makes it bad?  Put it into practice with the lab Disclaimer - a lot of this will be based on Healy, Chapter 2   Above all else, show the data

Edward Tufte</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Data with R</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/classr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/classr/</guid>
      <description>   Week Lecture Content Slides (pdf)     1 1 Oh the places you&amp;rsquo;ll go! An intro to R w1p1   1 2 Lab 1: Intro to R Markdown w1p2   2 1 Intro to dplyr w2p1   2 2 Lab 2: Data Import w2p2   3 1 Intro to ggplot2 w3p1   3 2 Lab 3: Data Viz Best Practices w3p2   4 1 Intro to tidy data w4p1   4 2 Lab 4: More on Tidy Data w4p2   5 1 More dplyr and R Markdown w5p1   5 2 Lab 5: Tidy data and Data Visualization w5p2   6 1 Guest Lecture with Scott Chamberlain    6 2 Review w6p2   7 1 Joins: Part 1 w7p1   7 2 Joins: Part 2 w7p2   8 1 Intro to Strings w8p1   8 2 Intro to Regular Expressions w8p2   9 1 Factors and Dates w9p1   9 2 Student Presentations (no lecture)    10 1 Topics Beyond the Class w10p1   10 2 Student Presentations (no lecture)     </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factors and Dates</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w9p1/w9p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w9p1/w9p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Basics of factors  creating/modifying when you do/do not want factors  Basics of Dates  Specifically, we&amp;rsquo;ll focus date calculations   Disclaimer  We&amp;rsquo;re obviously not going to cover all there is to know about factors and dates in one smashed-together two-hour lecture. If we had more time, we&amp;rsquo;d spend a week on each.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing Data</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w2p2/w2p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w2p2/w2p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Discuss reading in data  The rio package, and when you may want some additional flexibility Other packages for reading in data  Lab  Use R Markdown Read in data from two different sources Conduct some basic manipulations   rio  Super nice package - most of the time, it just works, regardless of the source file type.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to ggplot2</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w3p1/w3p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w3p1/w3p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Introduce the ggplot2 package  Note: There is a lot that we won&amp;rsquo;t cover today (it&amp;rsquo;s just an intro).
The ggplot2 package Today, we&amp;rsquo;ll primarily be covering the basics of the ggplot2 package. Much of this presentation is based on examples from the new ggplot2 book.
Part of the many reasons Hadley is a cool guy  (It&amp;rsquo;s no longer there, but if you want access to it let me know)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to tidy data</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w4p1/w4p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w4p1/w4p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Introduce the concept of tidy data Tidy a simple dataset together with tidyr Summarize and transform tidy data with dplyr Fit a few models and look at some extensions (the broom package) Practice a bit, if time allows (it probably won&amp;rsquo;t)  A little story first      It is often said that 80% of data analysis is spent on the process of cleaning and preparing the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Data Science with R</title>
      <link>/vita/ds/ds1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/ds/ds1/</guid>
      <description>EDUC 610: Introduction to Data Science with R    Week Lecture Slides     1 1 Oh the places you&amp;rsquo;ll go! An intro to R   1 2 Seeing the big picture   2 1 Intro to data viz 1   2 2 Intro to data viz 2   3 1 Intro to data wrangling 1   3 2 Data Import &amp;amp; data wrangling 2   4 1 Dynamic Documents 1: Intro to R Markdown   4 2 Intro to git and GitHub   5 1 More git &amp;amp; intro to dynamic APA manuscripts   5 2 Advanced R Markdown   6 1 Guest Lecture: Alison Hill   6 2 Introduction to tidy data   7 1 Continuing with tidy data   7 2 Finishing up with tidy data   8 1 Some data taming (focusing on factors)   8 2 Work Day   9 1 Review   9 2 Work Day    The table above will be updated as the class goes along</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Regular Expressions</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w8p2/w8p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w8p2/w8p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Basics of regular expressions  You&amp;rsquo;re not expected to be an expert from one brief lecture  Provide resources for learning more Purpose: Generally to make you aware of them  Disclaimer  Before we get started, I think it&amp;rsquo;s worth mentioning this is NOT a specialty area for me. Still working hard myself to understand all of this Today is mostly about exposure and awareness  Resources (Some of which I&amp;rsquo;ll reference and others I won&amp;rsquo;t) * Sanchez: Handling and Processing Strings in R (available here) * Li and Bryan: Regular Expression in R (available here)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Strings</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w8p1/w8p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w8p1/w8p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Basics of string data String operators  Cover both stringr and base functions  Special characters Pattern matching  Before we get started  In many cases, I&amp;rsquo;ve opted to show both base and stringr functions stringr is part of the tidyverse, and has some nice functionality, but many of the base functions are so common I think I&amp;rsquo;d be doing you a disservice if I didn&amp;rsquo;t also introduce them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joins</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w7p1/w7p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w7p1/w7p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  To get started today, run the following code. We won&amp;rsquo;t use it a lot, but we will use it some.
library(tidyverse) install.packages(&amp;quot;nycflights13&amp;quot;) library(nycflights13)  keys  Uniquely identify rows in a dataset. Variable(s) in common between two datasets to be joined. Primary keys: Uniquely identify observations in their dataset Foreign keys: Uniquely identify observations in other datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab 1</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w1p2/w1p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w1p2/w1p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Things to cover today  R Studio R Studio Projects Installing packages (specifically tidyverse) Reading in data (very briefly) The $ operator Super basics of manipulating data with dplyr R Markdown basics  R Studio [demo]
 Customizing the look/feel  Theme Syntax highlighting Panes  Keyboard shortcuts Snippets (briefly)  (consider the daily download version: https://www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More on Joins (lab)</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w7p2/w7p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w7p2/w7p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Load College scorecard data Load Earnings data Tidy and join Joins with data viz  semi- and anti-joins, mostly   Read in college scorecard data library(tidyverse) library(rio) library(janitor) scorecard &amp;lt;- import(&amp;quot;../../data/Most-Recent-Cohorts-Scorecard-Elements.csv&amp;quot;, setclass = &amp;quot;tbl_df&amp;quot;, na = c(&amp;quot;NULL&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;PrivacySuppressed&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% clean_names() head(scorecard)  ## # A tibble: 6 x 122 ## unitid opeid opeid6 instnm city ## &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt; &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt; ## 1 100654 100200 1002 Alabama A &amp;amp; M University Normal ## 2 100663 105200 1052 University of Alabama at Birmingham Birmingham ## 3 100690 2503400 25034 Amridge University Montgomery ## 4 100706 105500 1055 University of Alabama in Huntsville Huntsville ## 5 100724 100500 1005 Alabama State University Montgomery ## 6 100751 105100 1051 The University of Alabama Tuscaloosa ## # .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More on tidy data</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w4p2/w4p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w4p2/w4p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Review and discuss tidy data in more depth Practice tidying data  Reasons to prefer tidy data  More efficient storage and retrieval More scalable The tidyverse of tools will work much more efficiently  Read in the hiv data  Make some manipulations (just dplyr variety) to make the data look like the below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Regression in Educational Research</title>
      <link>/vita/mr/mr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/mr/mr/</guid>
      <description> EDUC 610: Multiple Regression in Educational Research    Week Slides     1 Welcome to multiple regression   2 MR w/2 continuous IVs   3 MR w/categorical IVs   4 Uncertainty and significance testing   5 Regression diagnostics   6 Partial and semipartial correlations   7 Interactions   8 Multi-model inference   9 Dealing with collinearity and non-linearity   10 Regression for prediction    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple regression with R</title>
      <link>/talks/gina/gina_mr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/gina/gina_mr/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Introduce R Very basics of R (object assignment) R packages Running multiple regression models Visualizing multiple regression models  Who am I? Daniel Anderson
 Research Associate: Behavioral Research and Teaching Dad (two daughters: 5 and 3) Quantitative educational researcher who loves R Primary areas of interest  R and computational educational research Open data, open science, and reproducible workflows Growth modeling (primarily through multilevel models)    Part of why I love R  Computer programming language = you can do ANYTHING!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh the places you&#39;ll go!</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w1p1/w1p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w1p1/w1p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Introductions Syllabus Introduce R Very basics of R (object assignment) R packages Guided practice (if time allows)  Overall purpose of today: Get you excited about R! Will be a lot of me showing, and not a lot of you doing. That will change quickly.
Who are you?  Please introduce yourself.  Name/Program of study and things you&amp;rsquo;re interested in Prior experience with R Why do you want to learn R?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>/vita/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/publications/</guid>
      <description>Peer-Reviewed Journal Articles  Tindal, G., &amp;amp; Anderson, D. (in press). Changes in Status-Service and Performance over Time for Students with Specific Learning Disabilities. Learning Disabilities Quarterly.
 Nese, J. F. T., Farley, D., &amp;amp; Anderson, D. (in press). The instructional characteristics of small-group, Grade 1 reading interventions applied in schools. Learning Disabilities: Research and Practice. Learning Disabilities: Research and Practice.
 Rosenberg, J, Beymer, P. N., Anderson, D., and Schmidt, J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w6p2/w6p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w6p2/w6p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  Agenda  Review where we&amp;rsquo;ve been  reading in data dplyr tidyr  Where to next? (briefly) Lab  Work on your final project   Tidyverse: Providing a grammar for&amp;hellip;  Graphics (ggplot) Data manipulations (dplyr) Tidying data (tidyr) Ever expanding specialized topics (not quite modeling yet, although there is some)  Reading in data rio makes it easy  Remember there are a bunch of different options you can specify</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software</title>
      <link>/vita/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/software/</guid>
      <description>Author I have authored the following R packages.
esvis Anderson, D. (2017). esvis: Visualization and Estimation of Effect Sizes. R package version 0.1.0. CRAN GitHub
The purpose of esvis is primarily to visualize differences in two or more distributions. It is an implementation and extension of ideas discussed by Andrew Ho (see, for example, here). Non-parametric methods for effects sizes are also implemented. For an introduction to the package, see here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survey of Educational Research Methods</title>
      <link>/vita/educ611/educ611/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/educ611/educ611/</guid>
      <description>Survey of Educational Research Methods This is a course I co-taught during the summer of 2018. The topics on which I lectured were:
 Course overview and research basics Validity, and sampling Measurement, RCTs, &amp;amp; quasi-experimental designs Review, Article Critique, and midterm  Each of the above links to the lecture slides.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks</title>
      <link>/talks/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talks/talks/</guid>
      <description>Talks Spring 2019  Some Advice on Data Viz  Talk for first year graduate students in a Psychology seminar on producing better data visualizations  AERA Reproducible Research Training: (part 1) AERA Reproducible Research Training: (part 2)  Training on open and transparent research with R and git/GitHub. April 7, 2019, Toronto, Ontario.  Evaluating Content-Related Validity Evidence Using Text Modeling  Talk for the annual conference of the National Council on Measurement in Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>/vita/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/teaching/</guid>
      <description># COE Data Science Specialization  I am currently in the process of leading the development of a five-course data science specialization in R for students in the College of Education at the University of Oregon, in collaboration with Drs. Alison Hill, Chester Ismay and Andrew Bray. Although the courses will be offered through the COE, it is anticipated that students from numerous social science departments will have an interest, given past enrollment in the R courses listed below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tidy data, data viz, and summaries</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w5p2/w5p2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w5p2/w5p2/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }   Tidy data is particularly important for ggplot2 because the job of ggplot2 is to map variables to visual properties: if your data isn’t tidy, you’ll have a hard time visualising it.
 Wickham, ggplot2 book, Chapter 9  Aesthetics  Aesthetics map a variable to a visual clue called a glyph When mapping a variable to a glyph, use aes().</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vita</title>
      <link>/vita/vita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/vita/</guid>
      <description>Vita All headers link to additional content Teaching I teach graduate courses in quantitative methods, usually with a data science focus, using R. I regularly post the materials from my courses on this website, which can be found by following the Teaching link.
Publications My publications to date have mostly been focused in the area of Educational Measurement. I have co-authored 13 peer-reviewed journal articles, with 4 as lead author.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>dplyr (and a bit of checking in)</title>
      <link>/vita/classr/slides/w2p1/w2p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/classr/slides/w2p1/w2p1/</guid>
      <description>em { font-style: italic }   strong { font-weight: bold; }  First things first: Cool stuff share! A bit of background on my pick  Equations within RMD look beautiful, but can be a pain  Must use \LaTeX (see examples here: http://www.statpower.net/Content/310/R%20Stuff/SampleMarkdown.html)    
 My pick: mathpix  See https://github.com/jonocarroll/mathpix   Generally works well regardless of surface (demo following)
 Others? Tidyverse: Providing a grammar for&amp;hellip;  Graphics (ggplot) Data manipulations (dplyr, tidyr) Ever expanding specialized topics (not quite modeling yet, although there is some)  dplyr: A grammar for data wrangling Take a guess - what do you think the following do?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>esvis</title>
      <link>/vita/esvis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vita/esvis/</guid>
      <description>The esvis package is designed to visually compare two or more distributions across the entirety of the scale, rather than only by measures of central tendency (e.g., means). There are also some functions for estimating effect size, including Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d, Hedges&amp;rsquo; g, percentage above a cut, transformed (normalized) percentage above a cut, the area under the curve (conceptually equivalent to the probability that a randomly selected individual from Distribution A has a higher value than a randomly selected individual from Distribution B), and the V statistic, which essentially transforms the area under the curve to standard deviation units (see Ho, 2009).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>